<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ieremiahs teares, or A sermon preached in York-minster vpon Trinity Sunday, in the yeare of our Lord, 1604 when the sicknes was begunne in the cittie. By Thomas Pullein vicar of Pontefract, sometime chaplaine of New Colledge in Oxford.</title>
            <title>Jeremiahs teares.</title>
            <author>Pullein, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1608</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10216</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20493</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106092</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841817</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841817</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6427</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10216)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6427)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1331:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ieremiahs teares, or A sermon preached in York-minster vpon Trinity Sunday, in the yeare of our Lord, 1604 when the sicknes was begunne in the cittie. By Thomas Pullein vicar of Pontefract, sometime chaplaine of New Colledge in Oxford.</title>
                  <title>Jeremiahs teares.</title>
                  <author>Pullein, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[42] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Iaggard, for Clement Knight,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1608.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴-E⁴ F²  (-A1, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Plague --  England --  York --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6427:1"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:6427:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Ieremiahs Teares,</p>
            <p>OR A Sermon Preached in York-minſter vpon Trinity Sunday, in the yeare of our Lord, 1604. when the ſicknes was begunne in the Cittie.</p>
            <p>BY Thomas Pullein Vicar of Pontefract, ſometime Chaplaine of New Colledge in Oxford.</p>
            <q>Oh that they were wiſe, then they would vnderstand this: they would conſider their latter end. <bibl>Deut. <hi>32. 29.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed by William Iaggard, for Clement Knight.</hi> 1608.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6427:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6427:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> To the Honourable Robert Askwith, Lord Mayor of the Citty of Yorke, and the Right Worſhipfull his Graue Aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciates and Brethren the Aldermen, all <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Graces, with wordly Proſperity in this</hi> life, and eternal happines in the life <hi>to come.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing of long time conceiued a purpoſe, (my good Lord) to giue ſome publicke Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of my Loue to your Honourable Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the place of my byrth, J began now in the latter end of your Lordſhips yeare, to conſider, that J could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue a fitter opportunity, for the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of my deſire. Whereupon, beeing loath to vſe any further delay, in letting paſſe ſo good an occaſion, neere loſt already, I was forced in haſt, the time ſo requiring, to looke vp my old Papers, to ſee if I could finde any thing worthy to preſent vnto your Lordſhip. And while I was thus occupied, I bethought my ſelfe, of that Sermon which heeretofore
<pb facs="tcp:6427:3"/>
I made in the City, when it was newly viſited with the late contagious ſicknes, being drawn thither at the earneſt requeſt of a Worſhipful friend. And this J thought the fitteſt, to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh at this time, for ſundry cauſes Firſt, to put vs in mind of the manifolde, Gracious, and Fatherly benefites, wherewith God hath bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vs aboue al the Nations of the Earth, and how we haue abuſed the ſame. Secondly, to ſet before vs the horrible ſins wee haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, with our monſtrous vnthankfulneſſe againſt his Maieſty. Thirdly, to renew a freſh the remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his ſeuere Chaſtiſements, lately, but moſt iuſtly inflicted vpon vs which we ſeeme to haue vtterly forgotten. And laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to admoniſh vs, that if neither his bleſsings nor puniſhments wil moue vs to repent &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend our liues, hee hath yet more fearefull iudgements, to aſtoniſh our rebellious harts, &amp; vtterly to make an end of vs, which though we haue eſcaped the plague, do ſtill threaten our ruine and deſtruction. All which points, I had rather ſhould be obſerued out of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon it ſelfe, then trouble this place with the repetition therof. The reaſon why I haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred
<pb facs="tcp:6427:3"/>
this vnto the end of your yere, was, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I had partly heard by generall report, &amp; partly ſeene with mine owne eyes, how hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably you haue performed your Office, and paſſed your yeare with as much credit &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe, as any of your Predeceſſors, I coulde not but reioyce in your Lordſhips behalfe, &amp; for a Teſtimony of my Gratulation, bringe with me this pore preſent, to the ſhutting vp of your yeare, not doubting, but your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip will take the ſame in good part.</p>
            <p>And thus (honorable, and right Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) commending this ſmall exerciſe to your diligent reading, &amp; carefull practiſe, with my harty Praiers to the Lorde, for the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of his bleſsings vpon your Citty, &amp; that it will pleaſe him to repleniſh the people vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your Gouernment with the knowledge of his heauenly truth, and feruent loue of his holy Goſpel, framing their harts in obedience thereunto to their eternal Saluation, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly take my leaue. <hi>Pontefract,</hi> this firſt of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary, 1607.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips and Worſhips to command in the Lord Thomas Pullein.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:6427:4"/>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:6427:4"/>
            <head>Ornatiſsimis viris, omni doctrinarum genere imprimis conſpicuis, D. Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di, Socijs, caeteriſque Alumnis Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legij Noui apud Oxonienſes debita vnicuique obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantia.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Vodecim plus minus elap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum eſt annorum interua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum (doctiſsimi viri, et fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres plurimum obſeruandi) ex quo inſignis veſtrae do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, Capellanus, eforo Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legij veſtri, in vineam Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minime contulerim. Quales exinde labores ſuſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perim, non dignos ſeuſeo, de quibus dicam. Hoc qualecun<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> opuſculum, ſi quid inde ſit emerſurum boni, Ciuitas illa, in qua natus fuerim et educatus, cui labor etiam iſte d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtinatus iampridem fuerat, optimo iure ſibi vendicat: vt vbi lucem ipſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum conſpexerim, quod a me primo profectum eſt, primum etiam in lucem prodeat. Si quid tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem vos interpellem, rogetis? dicam verbo: Nihil mihi viſum est indignius, quam vobis, vel incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultis,
<pb facs="tcp:6427:5"/>
velſaltem neglectis, quicquam moum in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licum prodire. Quicquid enim mibi eſt, vobis ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ccptum fero, vobiſque animi qua maxime poſsum gratitudine refero. Nullius autum rei magis ſum cupidus, quam vt vos labores meos, ſiue hos, ſiue alios in poſterum fortaſsis edendos, in veſtram tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telam ſuſcipere, quod recte dictum fuerit aequi con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulere, ſi quid proficiendi ſtudio deliquerim, indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genter condonare velitis. Deus in studia veſtra in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbat Spiritus ſui gratia, multoſque e veſtra ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietate dignos operarios in meſſem ſuam, emittere dignetur. Valete viri praeſtuntiſsimi, meque alum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Collegij veſtri, veſtrum in ſinum a linguis mordacibus confugientem ſuſcipite, fouete tueamini. Pontefracti, Calendis Ianuarij. 1607 (<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>)</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Veſtra ſocietati addictiſsimus Thomas Pulleinus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:6427:5"/>
            <head>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ieremiah 9. 1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Oh that mine head were full of Water, and mine eyes a fountaine of teares, that I might weepe day and night for the ſlaine of the daughter of my people.</q>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S God hauing tyed <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> faith, and by tryall found it ſincere, in walking obediently vnto his will, did plant his Church in <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> poſterity, being holie branches of a holy tree: ſo this Church God woulde not leaue deſtitute of his fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther grace, but as in mercy hee had freely choſen the ſame from among the reſt, ſo in his goodnes he bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it aboue the reſt. He ſent his Prophets from time to time, as dilligent husband-men to employ theyr Prayers both earely and late, for the dreſsing of hys Vineyard, and to do all things which might ſerue to make it fruitfull: that as hee had planted the ſame by himſelfe, ſo he might water it by his ſeruants, &amp; giue the increaſe by his ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Amongſt theſe ſeruants of God, whom the Lord had indued with the ſpirite of Propheſie, ſome were employed ſpecially among the <hi>Iewes,</hi> conſiſting of
<pb facs="tcp:6427:6"/>
the Tribes of <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Beniamin:</hi> ſome were ſent to the ten Tribes of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> which being reuolted from the houſe of <hi>Dauid,</hi> were now become a ſeueral king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of themſelues: ſome exerciſed a more ioynt function concerning both the kingdome of <hi>Iudah</hi> &amp; <hi>Iſraell:</hi> and ſome Prophecied more ſpecially concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning forraigne Nations. Of thoſe Prophets, whoſe commiſsion was to preach vnto the <hi>Iewes,</hi> our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ieremiah</hi> was neyther the laſt nor the leaſt: who being indued with rare and excellent gifts of God; as namely with feruent zeale, inuincible courage, and vnchaungeable conſtancy, beganne for to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie in a moſt corrupt and daungerous time, when the Booke of the Lawe was loſt, and neuer a coppie thereof extant for the inſtruction of the people. Whereof it is eaſie to gather, howe much a do the prophet had with the way-ward people, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing no common rule to direct them, either for the worſhip of God, or for the leading of their liues, (but euery man liuing as himſelfe liked beſt) both corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſeruice of God with their Idolatrous inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and defiling their conuerſations with horrible ſinnes. And after that, when the Booke of the Lawe was found, and publickly authorized by godly King <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> the people for all that became not much more tractable, though for his time reduced to ſome better order; yet afterwardes, like falſe-hearted <hi>Apoſtataes,</hi> they vtterly reuolted to their olde ſuperſtitions, and looſenes of life. And ſtraunge it is to conſider, what contradiction the holy prophet founde among that ſtif-necked people, who neither regarded the Lorde
<pb facs="tcp:6427:6"/>
that ſent him, nor the Ambaſſage hee deliuered, nor the iminent calamities which were ready to fal vpon their heads.</p>
            <p>None of all theſe thinges could make their ſtonie harts to repent, but on the contrary, they rayſed vp troubles and perſecutions againſt the prophet, ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him ſundry times in priſon, &amp; ſundry times ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his life, they remoued him from one dungeon to another, where his feet ſtucke faſt in the myre, in ſo much that he could not bee gotten out, till hee was drawne vp with ropes, as we ſee in the 37. &amp; 38. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. And yet notwithſtanding, he was not diſmayd, but patiently endured al theſe afflictions, and hauing conſtantly continued in the faithfull diſcharge of his propheticall function, for the ſpace of more then 40. yeares together, at length (as it is recorded of him) he was ſtoned to death in <hi>Egypt,</hi> by thoſe <hi>Iewes</hi> that wer fled thither for feare of the <hi>Chaldaeans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now to approch nearer vnto our text. When <hi>Iſaiah</hi> that excellent prophet of the Lorde, who had bin vehement in rebuking the ſinnes of the people, &amp; had laboured moſt earneſtly to bring them to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, could not preuaile with all his Trauayle, but loſt his labour, and ſpent his ſtrength in vain, hauing continued propheſying about the ſpace of threeſcore yeares: what hope could our prophet <hi>Ieremiah</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, who ſucceeded him, to preuaile more with that obſtinate people, then his predeceſſor had done, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both ſeruants of the ſame Lord, both employed in the ſame affayres, and both ayming at one marke, which was the repentance of the people, and theyr
<pb facs="tcp:6427:7"/>
preſeruation from deſtruction, depending vpon their repentance? Our prophet therefore, as hee was later in time, and the deſtruction of the <hi>Iewes</hi> nearer at hand, ſo his care was the greater, to frame and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe himſelfe in ſpeaking to the <hi>Iewes</hi> after ſuch a ſort, as his ſpeech might moſt deepely pierce the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſinnewes of their harts, and transfuſe it ſelfe into the marrow of their ſoules: not that he hoped to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiue any greater maters with them, then <hi>Iſay &amp; Ioel</hi> his predeceſſors had done, but to make them inexcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable before God, and that themſelues might ackno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the Lord to deale moſt iuſtly with them, when they ſhould feele the rigor of his iudgements, hauing bin thereof ſo often fore-warned. This therefore is the cheefeſt point in <hi>Ieremiah</hi> his doctrine to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, that nowe no hope of pardon was left vnto the Iewes. they had ſo long deſpiſed mercy, that now vengeance was come, and therefore they were to looke for nothing but to feele the waight of Gods heauy indignation. And for this they were to thanke themſelues; for thogh God be ful of patience &amp; long ſuffering, and is loth to puniſh ſinners when they do offend, yet hee will not alwaies ſuffer himſelfe to be mocked; his iuſtice wil not alwaies be ſleeping, but at length wil rowze vp it ſelfe like a ramping Lyon, and who is able to indure the fiercenes thereof. Though he giue his people a long time to repent, &amp; ſende his ſeruants to call them, to inuite them, to intreat them, &amp; to wo them, as a man doth wo a Virgin, whom he would make his wife, promiſing that hee wil be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful to their ſins, and not remember their iniquities,
<pb facs="tcp:6427:7"/>
that he wil deal with them in the greatnes of his loue, &amp; not in the rigour of his iudgement; that he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue and embrace them, as his deare children, &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow al good things vpon them both in this life, &amp; in the life to come, if they will amend their liues, &amp; turn vnto him; yet when they wil not be reformed, when they remaine impenitent &amp; incorrigible, and do har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den their harts againſt al theſe louing &amp; gracious ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions, how can the lord do leſſe then make them know and feele, that as he hath aboundance of ſweet mercies laid vp in ſtore for them that feare him, ſo his treaſure is not without ſharpe arrows, ſwords, and al kind of weapons, to gore the harts of al his enemies? Seeing then the Iewes were ſuch, how could the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ieremiah</hi> do leſſe, then ſounde out the trumpet of Gods wrath, &amp; thunder out the threatnings of Gods indignation againſt them? But what? did not <hi>Iſay</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, denounce the iudgementes of God againſt the Iewes? Yes verily, but with this difference: that <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> as he was vehement, ſo with his threatnings he alwaies mingled words of comfort, and gaue hope of pardon vpon amendment: but <hi>Ieremiah,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neither <hi>Iſaiahs</hi> preaching would moue them, nor the example of their bretheren (whom the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> had caried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way captiues, hauing vtterly deſtroied their kingdom) could work any remorſe in their harts, <hi>Ieremiah</hi> after al this, ſeeing the Iewes obſtinatly giuen ouer to hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of hart, he tels them plainly, that he muſt not now diſſemble with them, but as they were obdurate in their malice, without hope to bee reclaimed, ſo they muſt nowe prepare themſelues euer to beare the
<pb facs="tcp:6427:8"/>
burthen of Gods wrath, without hope to be releaſed.</p>
            <p>And we may further ſay, that God by the prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> did expoſtulate with the <hi>Iewes,</hi> hee pleaded hys cauſe againſt them, and brought them to their tryall; but by <hi>Ieremiah</hi> he conuinceth them, he findes them guilty, and giues ſentence againſt them, &amp; that ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence was performed euen in <hi>Ieremiahs</hi> time, who ſaw with his owne eyes the execution thereof.</p>
            <p>Seeing then, that the decree was paſſed, theyr de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction determined, and the ſentence irreuocable: Admonitions were vnprofitable, exhortations were vnfruitfull, to pray for them was forbidden: <hi>Thou ſhalt not pray for this people, neyther lift vppe cry or prayer for them, neither entreat me, for I will not heare thee,</hi> ſayth the Lord. <hi>Ier.</hi> 7, 16. This was the cauſe, that our prophet heere frames himſelfe to mourne, lament, and bewayle, the miſery, deſtruction, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity of the <hi>Iewiſh</hi> Nation: <hi>Oh that my head were ful of water, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And becauſe this Citty, and this land, hath bin as much bleſſed of God as euer <hi>Iudah</hi> &amp; <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> was, and the Lordes Gracious care to call you to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, that ye might not perriſh in your ſinnes, hath beene as great ouer you, as euer it was ouer them: &amp; that ſo many excellent Preachers, indued with ſuch variety of gifts, haue been ſent vnto you from ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places, beſides your ordinarie Preachers, whome the Lorde hath placed among you (which though they bee few through your owne fault, yet are they enow to make you without excuſe:) and al theſe haue not ceaſed to cry and cal on you, for the amendment
<pb facs="tcp:6427:8"/>
of your liues, to lay away your ſwearing, your drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe, your Whoredome, your falſhood and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit in buying, ſelling, and bargaining, your propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Gods Sabboths, your contempt of his word, your biting, extorting, and oppreſsing vſuries, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides infinite others your grieuous and abhominable ſinnes, and yet all in vaine; inſomuch that the Lord hauing laid his heauy hand vpon many places of this Land, to the deſtruction of many thouſands, hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunne alſo to ſtretch it out vppon this Citty, and is like to proceed further, and not yet to make an end, according to that of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 9, 12. <hi>The wrath of the Lord is not yet turned away, but his hand is ſtretched out ſtill.</hi> This is the cauſe, that hath mooued me, laying aſide all matter both of doctrine and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, to make choyſe of this place of Scripture, the better to occaſion me to lament &amp; bewaile both the hardnes of your hearts, and the greatnes of your puniſhment, and to ſay with the prophet <hi>Ieremiah, Oh that my head, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Prophet in theſe words doth ſignifie, that as their ſinnes were monſtrous, paſsing al meaſure, ſo the deſtruction was fearfull, which the Lord was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to bring vpon them, exceeding the meaſure of his ordinary Iudgements: and therefore, that hee was not able ſufficiently to bewayle the greatneſſe thereof. For great ſinnes procure great puniſhments, and great punniſhments are neuer without great ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and lamentation. Seeing therefore the punniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which God had prepared for the <hi>Iewes,</hi> were ſuch as they had neuer felt before, ſo the Prophet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth
<pb facs="tcp:6427:9"/>
to bewayl the ſame with ſuch a meaſure of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation, as neuer had bin heard of before: that the greatnes of his mourning might (if it wer poſsible) be fully anſwerable to the greatneſſe of their miſeries. In theſe wordes wee may obſerue two things: Firſt, the mourning of the prophet, and ſecondly, the obiect of his mourning. The mourning in theſe words, <hi>Oh that mine head were full of Water, and mine eies a fountain of teares, that I might weep day and night:</hi> the obiect of his mourning was, the ſlaughter of the people: <hi>that I might weepe day and night, for the ſlain of the daughter of my people.</hi> His mourning he ſets down in moſt pathe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticall and ſignificant terms. And this he doth by way of a Rhetoricall gradation; for he that weepeth, ſheds tears, and he that ſheds tears, muſt haue ſome inward moiſture that muſt be reſolued into tears. The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet therfore framing &amp; composing himſelf to weep, and in weeping to exceed meaſure, &amp; to paſſe mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, that he might not be interrupted in the courſe of his weeping for want of matrer to miniſtet ſuply of tears, he firſt wiſheth that his head were full of water, or rather, that his head were reſolued into water: for that commeth nearer the Haebrew original, <hi>Oh that ſome man wold make my head to become as water.</hi> In this great lamentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the prophet ſeemeth to fear nothing more, then that his head ſhould be drawn dry, &amp; that for lack of moyſture, he ſhould be conſtrained in time to forbear weeping, for (as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith) <hi>Nullus dolor longus eſt, qui magna est.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſorrow that is great cannot be long, for ſuch is the infirmity of nature, that nothing veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<pb facs="tcp:6427:9"/>
can bee of long continuance. Seeing therefore, that this ſorrowe was extraordinatie, becauſe it did ariſe of an extraordinary ocaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, here he ſets forth in extraordinary &amp; hyperbolicall formes of ſpeech, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther expreſsing his deſire, how hee would haue it to bee, then any hope he had that it could ſo be, &amp; not ſo much declaring what was poſsible &amp; likely to bee doone, as what was meete and conuenient to bee done.</p>
            <p>The thing therefore that our prophet deſireth is, firſt, that his head might be ful of water. It is not a ſmall quantity of water that will content him, but he would haue it ful of water. Nay, he would haue it reſolued into water, that ſo long as it is a heade, ſo long it might neuer be without water, to weepe and waile for the deſtruction of the people.</p>
            <p>But why doth hee wiſh that his head were full of water, and not rather his heart, ſeeing the heart is the ſeate of all the affections? Although the heart is the ſeate of the affections, yet the head is the ſeat of all the ſences, both inwarde and outward. And the head as it is the higheſt part of the bodye, ſo the mind which is the chiefeſt part of the ſoul, hath erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her throne therein, &amp; keepes there her reſidence, and from thence as from a Watch Tower, appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth all things, vnderſtandeth al things, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth all thinges that are brought vnto her by the outward ſences, which are her handmaids.</p>
            <p>This is the place where the minde doeth ſitt as Queene and Gouernour, and whatſoeuer it be ſhee
<pb facs="tcp:6427:10"/>
commaundeth, preſcribeth, or directeth, that the will and affections are ready to execute. And for that cauſe it is ſaid, <hi>Mens cuiuſque est quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>.</hi> The mind of euery man is the man himſelf. This is that which firſt aprehendeth the cauſe of griefe &amp; ſorrow, and by &amp; by Communicateth the ſame with the hart, which is preſently moued either to embrace or diſlike, as the minde Iudgeth the obiect to bee good or euil: Like vnto a Porter, who keeping the gate doth open it to his friend, and ſhuts it to his enemy. By this the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet in his Prophetical ſpirit, did foreſee that horible and bloody ſlaughter which ſhould be committed by the hoaſt of the <hi>Chaldaeans</hi> in the City of <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> And this did ſo deeply afflict and pierce his hart, that he could not containe himſelfe, but muſt needs break out into a moſt dolefull lamentation. And the better to continue and increaſe his ſorrow by miniſtring (as it were) food thereunto, he wiſheth that his head wer full of water: for as fire conſumeth wood and coales, and for want of woode or coales, the fire it ſelfe will conſume and be extinguiſhed; ſo weeping exhauſteth and draweth out teares, and when teares are conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, without ſupply, weeping it ſelfe muſt needes haue an end. And therefore, that a freſh ſupply might neuer be wanting, he wiſheth that his head might al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies abound with water. And for this purpoſe, the head is a more fit member then the heart: Firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the obiect of the affections is there apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and iudged of, and according to that iudgement the hart is affected.</p>
            <p>Secondly, for that the head is much larger, and of
<pb facs="tcp:6427:10"/>
a more capacious figure. Thirdly, becauſe it is more apt to receiue and hold water, both in regard of the ventricles or receptacles of the braine within, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for that it is ſtrongly fenced and enuironed (as it were) with a hard wall round about. And laſtly, for that the head hath better means to expreſſe the grief and ſorrow of the heart, both by mourning with the voyce, and by weeping with the eyes: And thus I am come to the ſecond point of the gradation, which is the ſecond thing that the prophet deſireth for the better expreſſing of his great ſorrow.</p>
            <p>He doth not onely wiſh that his head were full of water, but he declares the cauſe thereof; which was, not to keepe it ſtill encloſed in his head, but that from thence it might bee deriued and reſolued into briniſh teares, as faithfull witneſſes of his inward griefe. And to this end hee wiſheth, that his eyes might bee as a Fountaine, or (as it is in the Haebrewe Originall) a vaine of teares, which might be alwayes open &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſtopped, alwaies running and neuer dry. When a man would ſeeke a well, firſt he digges to get water, and when he hath found Water, his next care is, to draw it out, for ſuch needfull vſes, as occaſion requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth. Euen ſo our Prophets deſire is firſt; that hee might haue in his body a ſpringing wel, that his head might be the conduit; and for the better drawing of this water out, he wiſheth in the next place, that his eyes might be as ſpouts or as conduit pipes to powre forth this water. And it could not be, but ſo many as had not harts of flint, muſt needs bee moued with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhment, to ſee and behold this great lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<pb facs="tcp:6427:11"/>
And yet our prophet is not content with this, but he addeth, as the third ſtep of the gradation, <hi>that I might weepe day and night.</hi> It cannot content him to haue his heade full of Water, it cannot content him, that his eyes ſhedde teares: but as though this were no weeping, to expreſſe further, that all thys comes from the inward ſence &amp; ſorrow of his hart, he wiſheth that hee might weepe, and not ſimplie weepe, but weepe ſo, that his eies might neuer linne weeping, and his eye-lids might neuer cloſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to take any reſt, but be alwaies open to weepe day and night. Great was that mourning of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of <hi>Bethelem,</hi> when their children were ſlaine by the cruelty of <hi>Herod,</hi> whereof our prophet <hi>Ieremiah</hi> prophecieth Chap, 31. 15. which Teſtimonies is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by rhe Euangelyſt <hi>S. Mathew,</hi> in the ſecond Chapter and the 8. verſe, where hee applyeth the ſame to that ſlaughter of <hi>Herod:</hi> who ſeeing himſelf deluded by the wiſe men, cauſed al the male children of <hi>Bethlehem</hi> to be ſlaine, from two yeares olde and vnder, with intent to murther Chriſt, among the reſt <hi>In Ramah was a voyce herd, mourning and weeping, &amp; great lamencation: Rachael weeping for her children, &amp; would not be comforted, hecauſe they were not.</hi> But that lamentation, although it was bitter, yet was it not to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared with this of our prophet, becauſe that was only for the loſſe of ſome of their children, but here the prophet bewayleth that miſerable and fearefull deſtruction which ſhoulde generally come vpon all <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> as well young as olde, wherein there ſhould ſcarſe be any that ſhould ſcape &amp; not periſh, either by famine, ſworde, or by peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,
<pb facs="tcp:6427:11"/>
or at leaſt be carried into captiuity. It is much that <hi>Dauid</hi> ſayth of himſelfe, <hi>Enery night waſh I my head, and water my couch with my teares, pſal.</hi> 6, 6. Oh worthy practiſe for a penitent ſoule to imitate, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching euery ſinner that groneth vnder the burden of his ſins, to ſpend the nightes not in ſleeping, but in weeping, not in ſlumbring &amp; drowſynes, but in cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and calling to God for mercy, ſhedding the tears of true repentance? Worthy alſo is that to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, which is recorded of the ſinfull woman in the goſpell, Luke 7. who wept ſo aboundantly, that ſhe waſhed the feete of Chriſt, with the teares that trickled down from her eies. But this mourning of our prophet exceeds the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both, if not in greatnes, yet in continuance, whoſe teares diſtilling without intermiſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as from the conduit of a ſpringing wel, would be ſufficient, not only to water his couch, or to waſh the feet of thoſe that came nere him, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in time to ſend forth riuers of waters, like thoſe wherof <hi>Ezechiel</hi> ſpeaketh, chap, 47. which comming forth of the temple, were at the firſt meaſuring vp to the anckles, at the ſecond meaſuring vp to the loins, but at the third meaſuring, the waters were become as a riuer, that could not be paſſed. But why doth our prophet weep ſo immoderatly? That by his ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of many teares, ſome might drop out of theyr eies. For the prophet weeps not here for himſelf, but for the great miſety that ſhould come vpon the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. And though he was likely to ſuſtaine ſome part of their affliction, becauſe he dwelt among them, yet himſelfe was but one, &amp; not one of the greateſt; the ſtate of the Monarchy reſted in them, that is, in the king, in the Nobles, and the reſt of the people.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6427:12"/>
And therefore it was the publicke ſtate that he bewayled, whereupon euerie priuate mans condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion depended: as for himſelf he made no reckoning, and beſides, he knew that God who had employed him in that Meſſage, and had preſerued him hitherto from the bloudy hands of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> who had ſlayne many of the Lordes Prophets, was alſo able to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue him from the hands of the <hi>Chaldaeans,</hi> or to giue him fauour in their eyes, that they might do hym no harme, as it came to paſſe afterwards when the City was taken. <hi>Ier,</hi> 39, 11, 12. Seeing then, the Prophet doth weepe for the people, ſtandes it not with good reaſon, that they ſhould weepe for themſelues? when our Sauiour was led to be Crucified, many Women of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> followed him weeping. <hi>But Ieſus turned backe and ſaide vnto them, Daughters of Ieruſalem, Weepe not for me, but weepe for your ſelues, and for your Children, Luke</hi> 23. 28.</p>
            <p>He blames not their affection, but he ſpeakes by way of compariſon. He tels them, that if they knewe all, they had more cauſe to weepe for themſelues then for him. They wept for him, becauſe they loued him, but he went to die for them, becauſe he loued them. Iudge which of theſe had the greater loue? Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, ſuch was the ingratitude of the <hi>Iewiſh</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: ſuch was their impiety againſt God, their cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty againſt his Prophetes, and their impenitency in their ſinnes, that the Lord was determined vtterly to roote them out from being a Nation, and for euer to cut them off from being a people. And this he perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med about forty yeares after, by <hi>Titus</hi> the ſonne of
<pb facs="tcp:6427:12"/>
               <hi>Veſpaſian,</hi> the Romaine Emperor, who brought a final deſtruction vpon the <hi>Iewes.</hi> And this was the cauſe, that when our Sauior was come nere to <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> and beheld the City, he wept for it, <hi>Luke</hi> 19. 41, And in another place he ſaid, <hi>O Ieruſalem, Ieruſalem, which killeſt the Prophets, and ſtoneſt them that are ſent vnto thee, how often would I haue ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered thy children together, as the Henne gathereth her Chickens vnder her wings, and ye would not? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold your habitation ſhall bee left vnto you deſolate. Mat.</hi> 23, 37. By this complaint it appeareth that though our Sauiour mourned for the Citty of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> yet the people of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> had the greateſt cauſe to bewaile theyr owne miſery.</p>
            <p>Our prophet therefore in weeping for the people, he ſets them a preſident and rule to follow. It was their puniſhment that ſtrooke his hart with this inward ſorrow, and cauſed his eyes to ſhedde teares, and therefore he frames himſelfe to weepe, that by his weeping hee might wring teares out of their eyes.</p>
            <p>But ought not euery man to bee mooued moſt, with that which moſt concerneth himſelfe? Why then is our Prophet touched with a more liuely ſence of the Iewiſh calamities, then the Iewes that were to feele the ſmart thereof? Why doth he not wiſh that their heads were full of water, and theyr eyes fountaines of teares, that they might Weepe day and night for the deſtruction that ſhould come vpon themſelues? Oh their harts were hardned, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:6427:13"/>
that makes our Prophet to mourne the more. He had rebuked them for their ſinnes, but they would not amend. He had denounced Gods iudgements, but they deſpiſed his threatnings. When the falſe Prophets flattered them with <hi>Peace, Peace,</hi> to them they harkened. It is ſaide of our Sauiour Chriſt, concerning the Iewes, that hee did mourne for the hardnes of their harts, <hi>Marke,</hi> 3. 5. And heere our Prophet <hi>Ieremiah,</hi> when nothing would preuayle, he takes himſelfe to mourning.</p>
            <p>In this place we ſee, how needfull it is, that faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Paſtors be placed among the people when they are ignorant, to teach them: when they ſin, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh them: when admonitions wil not ſerue, to terrifie them with Gods iudgments: when nothing will preualle to mourne for them. The dumb dogs &amp; the ydle <hi>Non-reſidents</hi> do none of theſe thinges, the one cannot, and the other will not, and both of them haue bin the deſtruction of many thouſande ſoules, which will one day bee required at both of their handes. But what ſhall the faithfull miniſters do? Shal they tel the Drunkards, what the prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith vnto them? <hi>Wo vnto them that riſe vppe early to follow drunkennes, and to them that continue vntill night, till the Wine do inflame them? Iſa,</hi> 5, 11. <hi>Wo vnto them that are mighty to drinke Wine, and to them that are ſtrong to poure in strong drink,</hi> ver, 22. And what the Prophet <hi>Ioell</hi> ſaith. 1, 5. <hi>Awake yee Drunkardes, and howle, and weepe all ye drinkers of</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:6427:13"/>
               <hi>Wine, becauſe of the new Wine: for it ſhal be pulled fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your mouth?</hi> Shall we tell the Adulterers, what our prophet <hi>Ieremiah</hi> ſaith of them? 5, 7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Though I fed them to the full, yet they commit A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery, and aſſemble themſelues by companies into the Harlots houſes: they riſe vp in the morning like fedde horſes, &amp; euery man neyeth after his neighbors wife. Shall I not viſit for theſe things, ſaith the Lord? Shal not my ſoule be auenged on ſuch a Nation as this?</hi> ſhal wee ſay to the common and prophane ſwearer, as the wiſe man ſaith, <hi>Ezechiel</hi> 23, 9. <hi>Accuſtome not thy mouth to ſwearing, for in it there are many falles, neither take vp for a cuſtome the naming of the Holie one, for thou ſhalt not be vnpuniſhed for ſuch thinges.</hi> And ver. 11. <hi>A man that vſeth much ſwearing, ſhall be filled with wickednes, and the plague ſhall neuer go from his howſe?</hi> Or that which God himſelfe ſayeth in the third commaundement, that <hi>the Lord wil not hold that perſon guiltles that taketh his name in vain?</hi> Shall wee cry out againſt deceite in buying and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, againſt falſe weights and meaſures, againſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull and vnprofitable wares: againſt extortion, oppreſsion, and ſuch like. in condemning whereof the Scripture is vehement? Shall wee ſay to the V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer in the name of the Lord, <hi>Thou ſhalt take no v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury of thy Brother, thou ſhalt ſeeke no aduantage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, but thou ſhalt feare thy God, that thy Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may liue with thee. Thou ſhalt not giue him thy mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny to vſury, nor lend him vitels for increaſe. Le,</hi> 25. 36
<pb facs="tcp:6427:14"/>
Or that which in another place. <hi>Thou ſhalt not giue to vſury vnto thy Brother: as vſury of money, vſury of meate, or vſury of any thing that is put to vſurie, Deut,</hi> 23, 19.</p>
            <p>But what auayleth it vs to ſpeake of theſe things? your Pulpits haue ſounded with theſe exclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: but all in vaine. Theſe ſinnes haue ſo bewit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chedy our minds, partly with pleaſure, and partly with profitte, that they are become like the deafe Adder, that ſtoppeth her eares, and will not heare the voyce of the Charmer, Charme hee neuer ſo wiſely. They are ſo deepely rooted in your harts, through long continuance, that all their labour is in vaine, which ſhall endeuour to plucke them vp. They haue ſo lulled you aſleepe in the cradle of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, that it is eaſier for vs to raiſe vp <hi>Lazarus</hi> out of his Graue, then to bring you to any ſence or fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of your ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Seeing then, that all things are brought to this deſperate ſtate, the Lorde hath at length begun to waken vp his iudgements, to ſee if he can Waken you out of your ſleepe of ſinne. He hath begun at length to ſtretch forth his puniſhing hande vppon this Citty, which as it hath bin heauy vppon thoſe whom it hath touched, ſo it threatneth deſtruction to many moe.</p>
            <p>Oh then, what remaineth for vs, but with the
<pb facs="tcp:6427:14"/>
Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi> to weepe and lament? And heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, leaue mee not alone; but as <hi>Moſes</hi> and all the congregation of <hi>Iſraell</hi> wept before the dore of the Tabernacle when the wrath of the Lord was kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led againſt them. <hi>Numb,</hi> 25, 6. ſo it behoueth you all to ioyne with me as Actors in this lamentation. And firſt, you that are the Fathers and Gouernors of this Citty, as your ſinnes are not the leaſt (for I may not flatter you) ſo it is your partes to bee the formoſt in this great humiliation.</p>
            <p>But if you thinke the matter doth not concerne you, then I turne mee vnto the Lawyers, the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, and Artificers, with all the reſidue vvhoſe ſins haue conſpired together to bring downe Gods wrath vpon this Citty. And if they refuſe me, then where ſhould I make my mone, but to the women vvho haue good reaſon to be partakers of this com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon ſorrowe, becauſe their Pride, Vanity, Loftie lookes, Gayriſh attyre, Wanton geſture, &amp; other vices, haue not beene the leaſt cauſe to ſute this cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with this fearefull peſtilence? And if they diſdain to mingle their tears vvith mine, then haue I none to fly vnto, but the little children, that they at leaſt with their crying and weeping, may helpe to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe this dolefull lamentation.</p>
            <p>But if the hearts of all bee hardened: if neither Men, Women, nor Children will mourne vvyth mee, yet vvill I vvayle and mourne my ſelfe alone,
<pb facs="tcp:6427:15"/>
and ſay with the prophet, <hi>Oh that my head were full of water, and mine eyes a Fountaine of teares, that I might weepe day and night.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo I come to the ſecond part, which is the obiect of the Prophets mourning, <hi>that I might weep</hi> (for what?) <hi>for the ſlain of the daughter of my people.</hi> There is a time to laugh, and a time to Weepe: a time to ſow, and a time to reape, a time to commit ſinne, and a time to be puniſhed for ſin. The Iews had laughed a long time in ſecurity, but afterwards they mourned a long time in miſery.</p>
            <p>They had a long time ſowne the Tares of diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, but now they were to reape the fruite of wrath and vengeance. And as they had ſpent a long time in running the race of ſinne, ſo the Lorde at length found out his time to breake off their courſe, by powring his heauy iudgements vpon them. The prophet heere bewayleth the ſlaughter of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: he makes no mention of their ſins, which were the cauſe thereof. But in ſpeaking of the effect, hee implyeth the cauſe; for had it not beene for theyr ſinnes, the hoaſt of the Chaldaeans had not come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, and then that ſlaughter had not bin committed.</p>
            <p>Hereby he teacheth them, that it had beene in theyr power to haue preuented this lamentable ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, if they had repented of theyr ſinnes, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted
<pb facs="tcp:6427:15"/>
the time of Grace, when it was offered vnto them: but when they had deſpiſed mercy, &amp; had choſen to wallow ſtill in theyr ſinnes, now was the dore of mercy ſhut, and nothing but miſerable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to fall vpon them. This was the cauſe, that our prophet ceaſeth to bewaile their ſinnes, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteed thereof, he bewaileth the puniſhment which their ſinnes had produced.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That I might weepe for the ſlaine.</hi> He ſaith not, for thoſe that were dead among the people; for then, he might ſeeme to inſinuate, that this deſtruction ſhould be by ſome natural cauſe. But when he ſaith <hi>for the ſlaine,</hi> he ſhewes it was by violent death vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſword of their enemy. And heere conſider the deſtroyers, and the deſtroyed. The deſtroyers are deſcribed. <hi>Ier,</hi> 22, 23. <hi>Beholde, a people commeth from the North-countrey, and a great Nation ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe from the ſides of the earth. With Bow and ſhielde ſhall they be weaponed: they are cruell, and will haue no compaſsion, their voyce roareth like the ſea, and they ride vpon horſes, well appointed like men of warre, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, O daughter of Zyon.</hi> And Ier, 4, 13. <hi>Behold, he ſhal come vp as the clowds, and his Charicts ſhall be as a Tempeſt: his horſes are lighter then Eagles. Woe vnto vs, for we are deſtroyed.</hi> And Ier, 8, 16. <hi>The ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his horſes was heard from Dan, the whole Lande trembled at the neyghing of his ſtrong horſes: for they are come, and haue deuoured the Lande with all that is in it, the Citty and thoſe that dwell therein:</hi> The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyers then were the hoaſte of the King of <hi>Babel,</hi> clad in glitering armor, with their bloody weapons
<pb facs="tcp:6427:16"/>
their hands, vvounding, and ſlaying, and killing al that come in their Way, their Horſſes beſprinck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vvith blood, trampling vpon the dead Carkaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, cruſhing their flesh and their bones vnder their feet, vvhile they lay gaſping and panting, and brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing out the Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>The deſtroyed were the <hi>Iewes,</hi> ſignified by theſe Words, <hi>the ſlaine of the daughter of my people.</hi> Theſe are they whome the Prophet bevvayleth, hauing theyr flesh mangled, their bodies diſmembred, their limbes ſcattered vp and dovvne, here a legge, and there a hand, and there a head, and their bloud running too and fro in the ſtreets of <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But is the ſlaughter among vs ſuch a ſlaughter? Beloued, whether our ſins may prouoke the Lorde in his vvrath to make ſuch a ſlaughter of our peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, I leaue that to your vpright and due conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But the ſvvord of the enemy hath not yet made ſuch hauocke among vs. The Lord hath taken the matter into his ovvne hand. He hath ſent his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels to deſtroy euen from <hi>Dan</hi> to <hi>Berſheba,</hi> from the one end of the Land to the other, and the ſlaughter they haue made is a great ſlaghter. And the vvrath of the Lord is not yet turned avvay, but his hand is yet ſtretched out ſtill. Our ſinnes haue made our eyes to ſee that verified vvhich the Lord threatneth by the Prophet <hi>Moſes, Deut,</hi> 32, 42. <hi>I wil make mine arrowes drunke with the blood, and my ſword ſhall eat</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:6427:16"/>
               <hi>fleſh.</hi> If euer this iudgementwere accompliſhed in this land, it is nowe executed in theſe our dayes. The atrowes of the Lord are drunke with blood and his ſword do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h not ceaſe deuouring of mans fleſh. O wretched people, that would not be war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in time, to eſcape this fearefull iudgement of the Lord. You therefore that would not followe our counſell, when we exhorted you in the name of the Lord to forſake your ſins and amend your liues: now muſt you heare vs ſtrike vp the drum of Gods wrath, and ſound out the Trumpet vnto the Lords battels. Oye Angels, ſmite, ſlay, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, till the Lord ſhall command to make an end of killing, and till it ſhall pleaſe him to giue a ſign of retrait. But ſo long as your ſins ſtrike vp the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larum, ſo long will the Angels of the Lorde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy. Firſt therefore muſt we ſound the retrayte from ſinne, before the Lord wil ſound the retrait from the battell.</p>
            <p>But what? ſhall I put you in hope, that if yee preſently repent and turn vnto the Lord, the lord will forthwith ſtay his hande, and ſlay no more? Beloued I haue no ſuch commiſsion. When the Iewes had many yeares taken their full ſcope to roue and range licentiouſly in their ſinnes, deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the admonitions of <hi>Iſaiah, Ioel,</hi> and the reſt of that time: our Prophet <hi>Ieremiah</hi> comming af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them, finding no better entertainement then they had done, in the 4. chap. xii: ver, hee gyues
<pb facs="tcp:6427:17"/>
ſentence againſt them, which was too late to bee reuerſed. And though ſometimes hee inſert ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny excellent promiſes for the comfort of Goddes Church, that they might not vtterly deſpaire of mercy: yet thoſe promiſes wer not to take place, till firſt they had felte the ſmart of their former contempt; as we may ſee, <hi>Ier,</hi> 29, 10, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So the Lord hauing vouchſafed vnto vs the preaching of his Goſpell with al temporal bleſsings accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panying the ſame, ſo long a time, and in ſo graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a meaſure, as neuer nation vnder heauen, hath beene ſo bleſſed of God, as this Land, and this Citty; novv that our ſinnes haue as much abounded againſt GOD, as his mercies haue abounded towards vs, inſomuch that the Lorde could no longer with-hold his iudgements: how can we looke that this wrath of the Lord ſhould be ſo eaſily remoued, which wee our ſelues haue prouoked, til firſt we haue felt his ſcourge for our former vnthankfulnes? And yet it ſtands you vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, euen ſpeedily to repent, &amp; flee vnto the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God in his ſonne Chriſt, leaſt you bee not onely cut off by this ſword of the Lorde, but alſo periſh for euer in the world to come.</p>
            <p>The iudgements of God are of two ſortes, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther generall, prepared for the deſtruction of all the world, or particuler, for the punniſhment of certaine Nations, Kingdoms, Citties, or towns. The general iudgements are of two ſorts: Fyrſt, the Element of Water, whereby the old worlde was deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6427:17"/>
But this is no more to be feared: for God hath promiſed, that the worlde shall no more bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by a floud: and to that end he hath ſet his rainebow in the clowdes, as a ſigne of his Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, <hi>Gen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 19, 13. The other general iudgment is by the element of fire. 2, <hi>Pet.</hi> 3, 7. <hi>The heauens and earth, which are now, are kept by the ſame worde in ſtore, &amp; reſerued vnto fire againſt the day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and of the deſtruction of vngodly men.</hi> And a little after verſe, 10. <hi>The day of the Lord wil come as a theefe in the night, in the which the heauens ſhall paſſe away with a noyſe, and the Element ſhall melte with heate, and the earth with the workes that are therein ſhalt be burnt vp, &amp;c.</hi> But this iudgement god wil not execute til the end of the world, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſinnes of al mankind shal bee growne to full ripenes.</p>
            <p>The particuler iudgements are of many ſorts, but heere we wil not meddle with thoſe that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne particuler perſons, but ſuch as are inflicted vpon particular Nations, Kingdomes, Citties, &amp; Townes. And theſe are either extraordinary and leſſe vſual, as fire &amp; Brimſtone; wherewith <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi> were deſtroyed, <hi>Gen,</hi> 19, 24. and Earth-quakes, wherewith <hi>Antioch</hi> and manie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Citties were brought to extreame ruines, as we may read in the Eccleſiaſtical hiſtories: or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and ordinary, which are ſpecialy three, war, famine, &amp; peſtilence.</p>
            <p>Al theſe are sharpe arrowes which the Lorde
<pb facs="tcp:6427:18"/>
ſhooteth out againſt particuler Nations and Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties for the puniſhment of their ſinns. Of all theſe together ſpeaketh our Prophet <hi>Iere,</hi> 14, 12. <hi>When they faſt, I will not heare their cry, and when they of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer burnt offring, and an Obligation, I will not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept them: but I will conſume them by the ſword, &amp; by the famine, and by the Peſtilence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now which of all theſe iudgementes hath the Lord ſent vpon this land? He hath cauſed warres to ceaſe, he hath not ſent a famine amongſt vs, he hath in mercy laid vpon vs Dauids choiſe: vvho when he had ſinned, the lord offred him to choſe which of theſe three he wold, three months war, ſeaven yeares famine, or three dayes peſtilence. Of three three euils <hi>Dauid</hi> chooſed the laſt, as the leaſt, and thus reſolued: <hi>Let vs fall now into the hand of the Lord, for his mercies are great, &amp; let me not fall into the hand of man.</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24, 14. Seeing then we are in the hands of the Lord, why ſhuld we think much with the Lords viſitation? whoſe mercy doth euidently appeare in this, that vvhen our Sins had long cried to heauen for vengeance yet the Lord ſtil forbare to puniſh &amp; now when our sins would ſuffer him to forbeare no longer, yet it hath pleaſed him, without our desire, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, to lay on vs the eaſieſt of his iudgementes<hi>:</hi> wherefore; he hath not left vs without hope, that the ſame mercy, wherby he was moued to deale thus graciouſly with vs in allotting vnto vs thys
<pb facs="tcp:6427:18"/>
kind of puniſhment, the ſame will alſo moue him not to be too rigorous in the manner and order of inflicting thereof.</p>
            <p>Oh but (you will ſay) that is a fearefull iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and we had rather die of any other ſicknes, then of the plague. Oh, but I muſt anſwere you, that you muſt thanke your ſelues, and your ſins for it, which haue deſerued farre greater iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Shal we take liberty to our ſelues, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit what ſins it pleaſeth vs, and ſhall we abridge the Lord of his liberty? Shall wee not giue hym leaue to puniſh our ſins with vvhat kinds of pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishments it pleaſeth him? Seeing it coulde not ſtand with the courſe of Gods Iuſtice, but that ſame iudgment muſt needs come vpon this land, how coulde the Lorde ſend an eaſier iudgement then this vpon vs? Would it not be more gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous, to haue their bodies pinched with famine, that for the ſatisfying of your hunger ye ſhoulde be forced to eat the flesh of your ovvne children, as came to paſſe in the ſiege of <hi>Samaria</hi> 2: <hi>King.</hi> 6 29. Would it not be more grieuous, to ſee your houſes burnt, your goods ſpoyled, your wiues &amp; daughters rauished before your faces, and afteral this, your ſelues to be ſlain with the ſword of the enemy? Al vvhich calamities, beſides infinit mo are incident to the broyles of Warre. What thing could haue hapned more grieuous to <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dekiah</hi> King of Iudah, then beeing taken by the hoaſt of the Chaldaeans, to ſee his ſonnes ſlayne
<pb facs="tcp:6427:19"/>
before his eyes, and all the Nobles of <hi>Iudah</hi> putte to death, and after that to haue hir own eyes put out, and after all that, to be bound in chaynes, &amp; carried captiue to <hi>Babel? Ier,</hi> 39. Al this might the Lord iuſtly haue brought vpon vs<hi>:</hi> and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haue not we good cauſe to admire and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie his goodnes, in taking the Chaſtiſement of our ſinnes into his owne hands, and not deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vs ouer to the will and pleaſure of our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes.</p>
            <p>And yet it cannot bee denyed, but that this is alſo a grievous iudgement, though eaſie in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of the other two: for it is accompanyed with terrour, danger, &amp; great diſcomfort. When we conſider, how men and Women, that were luſty and ſtrong, are ſuddenly laide along in the duſt of the earth. Oh this is terible and fearefull to thoſe that be liuing! When we conſider, how the infection is deriued from one to another by waies and meanes, neither viſible nor ſencible, that no man knowes where he ſhal bee ſafe: Oh, this makes the ſicknes exceding dangerous! when we conſider the miſery of ſuch a time, how euery man will bee doubtfull to accompany with hys neighbor, for feare to take harme, and carefull to ſhun thoſe that bee infected: Oh, what great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfort is this to the viſited perſons, and what increaſe of feare to thoſe that be well? And heete you may conſider the ſtate of thoſe that be infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: when this coutagious ſicknes shal enter vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:6427:19"/>
any of your bodies. Firſt, it fils the head full of paine, and then it weakneth the ſtomacke, and makes it able to hold nothing. And after when it hath by little and litle ouercome nature, being not longer able to withſtand the force thereof, it do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth as a Captaine, who having won a City, forth with he ſpreads his Banners, and diſplaies his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes on the top of the wals, in token of victory. So this cruel Tyraunt when hee hath gotten the maiſtery, diſplayes his Enſignes on the Wals of our bodies. He fils the skin full of ſpots as the to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of death, which at the firſt are red, shewing his cruelty: then they are blewish, shewing death to approach: And laſtly, they grow black, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee are put in mind of thoſe horrible torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts that followe after death in the fire of hel. And when they are dead, hovve shal yee bee buried? Which of your neighbors vvil accompany your corpes to the graue? And thus, by the iuſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of GOD, thoſe that haue ſinned wilfully, are buried shamefully.</p>
            <p>What profit haue ye had then of thoſe things, vvhereof yee are now ashamed? the end of thoſe things is death. <hi>Rom,</hi> 6, 21. This (methinkes) shoulde ſtrike your harts vvith remorſe, &amp; moue you to crie and cal vpon god, for mercy and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of your heynous ſinnes, vvith teares of true repentance.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6427:20"/>
But hath the Lorde brought vpon vs ſuch a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable time? See then what alteration the lord can make. Before, nothing was heard in this Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but myrth and melody, muſicke and dancing, nothing was vſed, but feaſting and banquetting, quaffing and carowſing: Come, where ſhall wee drinke the beſt wine? where is the ſtrongeſt Ale to be had? But now, no ſpeech: but where is the Sicknes? What freſh houſes bee visited? Howe many are dead? Loe, this is the change that the Lord hath made. Before we followed Sinne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we wold not avoid it, but now we avoid ſin becauſe we cannot follow it. Before, we ſpent the time in committing Sinne, but now is the tyme come to ſuffer puniſhment for your ſinne. What will now the Adulterers doe? They muſt leaue hunting the Harlots houſes, leaſt the Angell of the Lord meet them by the way. What wil now the couetous Vſurers do? Let him humble him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in prayer and faſting, let him cry and call to God for mercy. Let him do as <hi>Zachaeus</hi> did, <hi>Luke</hi> 19. euen reſtore that which hee had wrongfully gotten, that GOD may bee mercifull vnto hys ſoule.</p>
            <p>O<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wretched man, what will thy vvealth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit thee or thine, when the Lord ſhall take avvay both thee and thine, and giue thy ſubſtance vnto ſtrangers? Oh, vvell had it beene for thee, if thou hadſt never taken penny Vſury in all thy life.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6427:20"/>
When you were before admoniſhed of theſe Iudgments in the name of the Lord, you thoght it came but from men, ſpeaking out of the heate of their owne affections, but now the Lord hath ratified and confirmed by his owne hande from heauen, that the threatninges denounced by hys faithful Miniſters againſt the impenitent, are not of man but of God.</p>
            <p>This is the note that Moſes giues whereby a true Prophet may bee diſcerned from the falſe<hi>: When a Prophet ſpeaketh in the name of the Lord, if the thinge followe not, nor come to paſſe, that is the thing which the Lord hath not ſpoken, &amp;c. Deut,</hi> 18, 22. <hi>But when the word of the Prophet ſhall come to paſſe</hi> (ſayth <hi>Ieremy) then ſhall the Prophet be known that the Lord hath ſent him. Ier,</hi> 28, 9. That ſome fearefull Iudgement was like to fall vpon the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, euery man mighr ſee, that had but a hart to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the ordinary proceedinges of Gods former Iudgements, and the horrible ſins that were eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where committed.</p>
            <p>But what manner of iudgement it would proue fleſh and blood could not diſcerne, till nowe the Lord hath reuealed the ſame. And the iudgment we ſee, is the iudgement of a plague: which yet is not alone. I would it brought not pouerty and famin with it. You are almoſt as a Citty beſied<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged<hi>:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:6427:21"/>
and there be many flee from you, but who comes in?</p>
            <p>The Countrey is now as much affraid of you as you haue beene heeretofore affraide of others. Now is the time for you that bee rich, to make you frends with the vnrighteous <hi>Mammon:</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake not your poore neighboures, flee not from them in their greateſt diſtreſſe. At leaſt if you flee, releeue them with your purſes, and ceaſe not to pray vnto God for them. Spend ſomething for his ſake, that ſpent his bloude for you. But as for you, vpon whom the charge of Gouernment do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth lie, whether you bee the chiefe Magiſtrate, or ſuch as are Aſsiſtants vnto him: the Lord hath ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you to reſidence.</p>
            <p>Your Chriſtian Charity, to releeue the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed, your prouident care to prevent daunger, your Godly wiſedom to ſer downe good orders, your paines and induſtry to ſee the ſame obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and your Authority to puniſh the diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, was neuer more needefull then at this time. And if any of you depart, be ſure the hand of the Lord can folow you, whetherſoever you go. And well may you feare, that rather then ye ſhould e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape, death wil enter in at your Windowes, as our Prophet ſaith in the one and twenteth verſe of this Chapter.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6427:21"/>
The children of the Prophets ſaid vnto <hi>Eliſha,</hi> 2. <hi>King,</hi> 4. 40. <hi>Mors in ollâ, vir Dei. O thou man of God, death is in the pot.</hi> But wel may you fear, that there will be <hi>Mors in domo, mors in ollâ, mors in lecto, &amp; mors vbique: Death in the houſe, death in the pot, death in the bed, and death euery where.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it bee Gods will, you ſhall bee ſafe any where, if it be not Gods will, you shall be ſafe no where. Well may you hope of Gods preſeruation and bleſsing, if you faithfully ſerue him in the place where he hath ſet you: And well may you feare his wrath &amp; vengeance, if ye flee from the charge which he hath laid (euen in this time of viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vpon you.</p>
            <p>But what need, haue I to admoniſh you, whoſe wiſedome and godly care doth evidently ſhew it ſelfe this diſtreſſed time? I will onely ſay this and ſo conclude. If you would haue your Citty flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, bee carefull to furnish it with ſtore of Gods Preachers.</p>
            <p>For aſſure your ſelues, that the more the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell is ſincerely preached, the more wil ſinne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay, and the more will the true knowledge and feare of GOD be planted &amp; grafted in the hearts of the people. And this will be the onely meanes to remoue the iuſt vengeance and wrath of God from this Citty, and procure his bleſsings to bee powred vpon you.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6427:22"/>
Thus much I thought good in diſcharge of the duety and loue I beare this Citty, as a Neighbor child to deliuer vnto you. The Lorde bleſſe the good meanes ye vſe for preſeruing your City, &amp; grant a gracious ſucceſſe thereunto, that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, if it be his will, may ſpred no further: If ye preſently repent, and that vnfainedly, I doubt not, but God in mercy will remoue the plague if not, yet will I not ceaſe to weepe for you. (<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>)</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <hi>Epheſians</hi> 3, 20. 21 <hi>Vnto him that is able to do exceeding abundantly, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all that we aske or thinke, according to the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer that worketh in vs, be praiſe in the church by Chriſt Ieſus, throughout all generations for euer, Amen.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6427:22"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
